okay hello welcome everybody to the
active inference institute's second
episode of our Mor stream Series so
these sessions are intended as a space
to Showcase and discuss the intersection
between neuromorphic Computing so brain
inspired Computing and active inference
um if you're new to neuromorphic
Computing I did give a short primer in
the first session which is available on
YouTube so the format is that our guest
speaker will present in the first part
then there's a Q&A and then a wider
conversation for the rest of the call so
our first ones featured uh David Capel
who's currently joined us again today
thank you David and he gave an
absolutely fascinating talk about um a
free energy model to uncover the role of
noise in the brain so it's like active
influence at the sinapse and today's
episode features Alan ller he's a
postdoctural scientist at cortical labs
in Melbourne Australia cortical Labs
being the company behind the very
interesting dish brain paper which
recently came out so he specializes in
synthetic biological intelligence and
has a PHD in neuromorphic Nano WI
networks from the University of Sydney
he also has almost three sorry over
three years of experience in designing
learning tasks and algorithms for brain
inspired systems and today he's going to
be presenting some really interesting
research on neuromorphic nanowire
networks and so if you want to share
your screen
absolutely thank you all right can you
see this all
good yeah all good all good fantastic so
thank you very much for having me um and
thanks for the wonderful introduction um
not much more to say about myself about
so that was perfect summary um yeah
today I'm going to talk mostly about my
PhD research which I finished last year
from the University of Sydney which was
in uh neuromorphic Nano networks and
that's quite a mouthful we'll definitely
get into what that is don't worry
hopefully by the end you'll be expert um
and I'll also touch a bit at the end
about what I'm working on at cortical
Labs at the moment and there's quite an
interesting link they're slightly
different but hopefully we'll get
through that so just a bit of an O
overview of how today is going to go I'm
going to give a very brief background I
imagine a lot of the people who are
interested in this kind of topics know
quite a lot about Ai and the state of uh
AI at the moment but just in case you
don't I'll give some background and and
go over that um EXP what Nano networks
are explain how what we actually do how
we model these systems and you know how
we actually apply these systems and then
at the end just give a brief overview of
what I've been working on for the last
year or
so so let's start with a bit of a
background so the brain the the original
inspiry or inspiration for artificial
neural networks AI kind of this machine
learning idea behind AI
was the neuron um the most basic Ann is
called a perceptron and it was sort of
in the 50s and 60s it was um created to
mimic the idea of this inputs into a
neuron from this sort of dendrites into
the through the cell body into the axon
and then across as an output into
different neurons and that's sort of the
idea that we have that's sort of what
became this beginning of uh artificial
neural and AI in general um and so but
but there's there's quite a few key
differences between neurons and the
structure of neurons in the brain and
how we Implement our perceptron Ann
interpretation of these neurons mainly
there's the idea behind vum AR vman
architecture which is what how we pretty
much Implement all of our Computing
these days compared to how the is
structured uh so in most modern AI
systems we implement this uh software of
AI on a hardware Von Norman Hardware
where we have this separation between
Computing processing and memory and we
have to bus information back and forth
from the CPU to the memory which is
quite a big bottleneck it takes quite a
lot of time to do that and that's pretty
much the main kind of limitation of of
this uh architecture whereas in the
brain there's sort of this integrated
idea of memory and processing that
happens at in the synaptic kind of uh
gaps between neurons in in neural cells
in chemical processes all that kind of
stuff occurs simultaneously and so we're
trying to overcome this bottleneck of
this busing information back and forth
which actually takes quite a lot of
energy and quite a lot of time the main
way we've been doing this is adding more
transistors this is sort of how the
structures are built it using
transistors more of those transistors
are added so that we can have more and
more computer processing this is what's
called Moors law and you may have heard
of that before but the idea is over the
past few decades from the beginning of
the perceptron which I introduced we've
sort of seen this two-year doubling idea
of computer processing power and energy
requirement and then in the last sort of
decade or so we've seen that this is not
a linear well still linear but it's not
quite as simple this relationship it's
not a doubling of energy and power we're
seeing this 3.5 3.4 month doubling of
requirement for power um so more and
more and more transistors are required
to do Ai and Ann kind of uh processing
and more and more power is therefore
required which is a big issue why is
this a big issue uh well firstly I'll
get i'll get back to that in in a bit of
a second but importantly um another
important aspect between you know the
brain and well Norman architecture
another difference is this brain
circuitry idea um and so while modern
applications of AI are really really
really good at uh you know um uh object
recognition and patent recognition uh
they've able to beat humans in lots of
things like that but their original uron
inspired architecture which I discussed
from the perceptron has transformed into
much more complicated system that's
reliant on on these higher and higher
power requirements and energy
requirements and are held back by this
bottleneck um and the feed forward
structure that we see that we all quite
familiar with where you have this input
layers into hidden layers uh into an
output layer where information Flows In
from the left goes through these layers
and out to the right it's an inherent
approach in AI there is some recurrence
that can be introduced but even that's
quite a simple um method and this is
highly highly different to biological
neural networks uh we see a very
different structure we see a very
different kind of functionality even in
these recurrent networks and so the
question is you know humans behave at
least sometimes intelligently with
significantly low energy requirements
you know you and I only need few meals a
day worth of energy the brain works at
around 20 watts of
information of energy sorry um and in
order to try and capture this kind of
intelligence and and and processing
capacity of the brain um we need to try
and overcome these bottl necks and
structural issues that I've mentioned
briefly that AI faces and so to do that
we can turn to the brain for inspiration
um and then the question that I was
asking during my PhD is how can we
capture physical nature of biological
intelligence so that's a brief
background of where the state we're in
and this is where neuromorphics enters
right that's the background behind what
we
were what the state we're in but
neuromorphics is one suggestion into how
to um solve this so neuromorphics the
term neuro comes from neuron morphic
meaning mimicking or copying uh
neuromorphics uh sorted into two main uh
categories one is the idea of
neuromorphic chips which is something
that you is probably more familiar to uh
similar to you know uh computer chips uh
seos electronic electrical chips stuff
like that and they're used as mainly AI
accelerators so how do we Implement
current AI models the software on this
new hardware um to get more neural
mimicking behavior and redu power
requirements and something that other
people might be more familiar with is
spiking neural networks where the idea
is we take traditional artificial neuron
networks and we turn them into this
binary input output or binary inputs and
binary outputs where it's just ones and
zeros and so you get significantly
reduced amount of data that you have to
deal with the weights are significantly
um more simple to deal with and so this
is a much easier kind of uh data set to
deal with and uses a lot more a lot less
energy as well on the other hand we have
this memristive systems and so
memristive systems
are systems that have this thing called
conductance-based
synapses uh where the the idea behind it
the word Mista oristive comes from Mista
which is a variable resistor and pretty
much it it exhibits memory as the kind
of current a hysteresis in a current
response curve that might not mean
anything but I'll explain that to you in
a little bit pretty much the idea is
that we get these memristive systems
that are much more uh biological like
when they're self assembled much more
array likee when they're array assembled
but they have this more uh nonvolatile
they have this more interesting Behavior
than neuromorphic chips do so there's
some examples of this these type of
systems uh Intel and IBM mainly work on
a AI accelerators in ly here and true
north um through the human brain um
through human brain project we have
developed uh Spa brain scales and a few
other models to try and Implement
spiking neuron networks which try and
represent replicate spikes in the brain
neurons and then memoris of crossbar
arrays this idea where you have these
sort of metal metal bottom and top
electrodes you have this cell in the
middle and you get flow of energy
electricity through that I'll explain a
lot more about this later it's just sort
of a bit of an
the thing that we are focusing on today
though is something called Nano networks
which fall into the self assembled
networks which means they assemble into
a network from the bottom up rather than
what you might imagine these other three
categories do in this kind of top down
clean lab
fabrication um e
experience and that makes them a lot
more similar to biological systems so
that's a a big mouthful but we'll get
we'll break it down a bit more so what
are nany networks well Nano networks are
typically made out of a a simple
material like a silver material um
they're Nano so they're really really
tiny on the orders of nanometers in
width about a thousandth of a hair width
of a hair um and they get to about five
to 10 micrometers in length so they're
really long and very very thin quite
similar to to a neuron a neuron and on
the right here you see an example of
what a neuro a nano Network looks like a
silver Nano Network so made out of
silver material compared to an example
of what a biological system look like so
there there's quite similarity quite
significant similarities in the
structure of how they look um so what
happens is we deposit these Nano these
these silver wires onto a glass
substrate usually
and they self assemble so they assemble
into this network and they start to
cross over each other so you can see
wherever um let me Point get the pointer
out where is the
pointer sorry there we go so wherever a
wire crosses over another wire we assume
that there is a junction or aapse
similar to you know where a dendrite
axon connects into a dendrite in neural
structures and so the idea behind this
the structure is resembles itself and
the function also resembl itself that's
what these two graphs at the bottom look
like so when we zoom into these kind of
uh Junctions as you can see here that's
a zoom in of that we get this uh silver
two silver wires are represented here we
get this in um insulating polymer in
between it's just a simple plastic
called PVP polymer um in between and
then when that is off meaning when
there's no electric current being passed
into the system nothing special happens
the W the wires aren't actually touching
each other there's no um electrical
conductivity but then when we turn it on
when we feed in some kind of input
voltage input pulse like is shown here
we see this ion migration this flow of
atoms positively charged atoms from one
of the wires to the other through this
plastic polymer and this is what we call
like a switch it's it's similar to what
an action potential kind of looks like
where action potentials occur and then
you get this uh increase in conductivity
in the membrane of the neuron we see a
similar behavior in
nanowires this is sort of the basic
blocks of how neurons communicate with
each other for those of you who don't
know how that uh happens um and we see a
very very similar kind of response
occurring in these uh Nano now I
mentioned memory
before
mistas have this property of when this
uh switch like Behavior occurs when you
get this uh nanofilament forming between
across here uh you get it's a nonlinear
Activation so it's not predictable it's
quite a difficult thing to model and
when it forms it has memory for previous
times previous signals that have
occurred that have been input into the
system so it forms at a certain Pace
nonlinear Pace once we stop that pulse
it starts to Decay slowly back across
the network at a different rate than
what it
originally uh formed so you get this
these multiple complex behaviors
occurring and because of that decay you
slowly like uh the the ions Decay very
slowly and imagine you've stopped the
signal for a couple of minutes the the
bridges halfway and then you you start
the signal again that bridge is going to
form a lot quicker than a bridge that
hasn't been formed previously so that's
where we get this memory aspect from it
that's a junction level memory we also
get all the beautiful recurrent um
behaviors of you know information isn't
just free forward um forward blowing
like in um like in artificial neural
networks we get this kind of uh
recurrent activity that information
flows in all directions in these
networks which is really really
important for information processing
biological like information processing
okay I've talked a lot more than I
thought I would so um let's power
through
um you can take your time it's no
problem great one really important
really interesting thing about Nano wise
is we can model them in uh graphical
representation where we take the wires
and we represent them as nodes the these
actual wires and whenever there's a
sinapse or a crossover between the
Junctions we can res represent those as
edges and so that really helps us to
look at the structural properties and
also the functional um connectivity of
these networks um so this is an example
of what we've done with a model you can
take a real nany Network um and you can
model the den it you can model the
length of the wires which we can measure
relatively difficultly but we can
measure them and then you can construct
a simulated version of it which is
definitely not one to one that's one
limitation that we have is very
difficult to model exactly the same but
it is experimentally validated meaning
that the activity that we see in the
simulated Network we see similar
conductance similar current similar
voltage in the real Nan and what's
really lovely and what I've um published
in first PhD paper is you can model
these uh these Nano in a graphical
representation as I mentioned before and
then compare them to other structures
that occur in the real world for example
a a fully random network over here a
completely lattice likee Network where
each node is just connected to its
nearest neighbor and then our NY Network
compared to a very simple biological
system which is called C elegant so what
we see is is that our biological Nano
network is much more similar sorry our
bioinspired neuromorphic Nano network is
much more similar to biological systems
like the celegans than it is to random
networks or these lattice like objects
and these lattice sort of like um
structures is what we see in typically
in cosos chips or Compu computer
chips um uh a bit more about the
modeling I've explained a bit about how
this conductivity uh this low to high
conductance occurs but we can model that
um using a mathematical equation for
those of you who like maths this is the
only equation that I will share in this
presentation I don't like having uh
equations on presentations but it's a
pretty cool thing to see pretty much we
can model when the voltage is higher
than what we have V set state which is
shown in this graph here so the voltage
is on the x-axis the current and the y-
AIS once there's a voltage set once we
reach a v set and once our voltage is
higher than that we have this kind of
switch that is on so we get in a high
conductive phase and then when the um
derivative of this Lambda function which
models this kind of filament is at zero
we have and when the voltage is between
uh this set State and the reset state
that we have we get this kind of
activity where it slowly decreases the
current decreases and flips and then
when the voltage is lower than reset we
get back to the off state where the is
at zero so this is what I was mentioning
mistas have this pinched hysterisis
curve that's what you see here this this
is called the pinched hysteresis curve
and this is sort of the idea with where
we want to see this kind of uh nonlinear
memristive
activity that's what makes a nanowire a
neuromorphic system
interesting um don't worry about it if
that's too much jargon for you it's just
a bonus for maths whoever like likes the
maths in here um so a bit more of a a
visual explanation of how this what the
nanowire network is actually doing this
is a model of the the network we've
simulated um where we have this input
electrode up here which is represented
by this green uh star and then we have
an a drain or an output electrode bottom
right here we feeding in a voltage uh a
standard voltage bias simple DC voltage
bias and we start to see each one of
these wires as I mention each one of the
wires is me is modeled by a DOT here and
each one of the connections between the
wires is modeled by an edge and you
start to see this kind of increase in
current flow that's what this is showing
current flow across the network from uh
the the source to the drain you see this
what what we call a winner takes all
pathway where the a path is formed where
these Junctions switch on so all of
these Junctions are at that on high
resistance State and all the others are
not yet and then you start to see like
more parallel paths beginning to
activate once that original path is um
formed which is a really interesting um
functionality that we can model we also
see this network level kind of increase
in G G is conductance so it kind of
models the it's the inverse of the
resistance so pretty much we start at a
very very high resistance State and then
we or low conductance and then at some
point and that point is at the the path
of lease resistance when the drain and
the the source and the drain are
connected we see this massive increase
in conductivity massive decrease in
resistance and that's that swap between
low resistance to a high resistance
State we see that at a network level as
well as an individual Junction level
which is really interesting behavior um
this is this sort of nonlinear
activation function which might look
familiar to some of you that have played
with artificial intelligence before for
those of you who haven't this nonlinear
nonlinearity is sort of how we do our um
calculations and transformations in um
hidden States it's you know it's this
there's different types of nonlinear
activation functions but there's the
retic and linear activation functions
anyway not important this is sort of
what this system does inherently we
don't have to train it to do that it
just that is the inherent properties of
this network um whereas in uh artificial
new networks we sort of have to play
around to get what the best model is to
fit that
um the memory aspect which I mentioned
also happens at a network level not just
a junction level so if you remember I
mentioned that each filament has memory
for what happened previously the network
also has that memory and what you can
see is when we're feeding uh a bunch
of uh short small pulses for a short
amount of time you get this increasing
conductance at the network level PR what
I explained previously and then it sort
of resets back to its original state
after a certain amount of time uh that's
because each one of those Junctions that
I've mentioned here that is activated
takes a while to Decay and go back to
its normal State and eventually it all
goes back to normal but if you increase
that uh the number the amount of time
that you're in inputting this voltage
and the number of voltage pulses you can
get the network into this kind of steady
state where it doesn't reset for quite a
long time and so you see this full
Network kind of activation level similar
to longterm memory or long-term
potentiation compared to short-term
memory these are just some really cool
um things that we've seen in the network
it's you know much more complex than
than I have time to really delve into it
but I just if you have more questions
please feel free to ask I can I can
answer as many as as needed um and so a
lot of background a lot of kind of
information dump but what can we
actually do with these what is why are
these cool you know why are we even
interested in these well firstly we have
to understand how we apply these so as I
said we take these Silver nanowires And
We dropcast Them meaning we take a
little pet we take um from a pre um
created mixture of these PVP um silver
Nano networks and we put them in the
middle of an electrode array that we've
set up so an electrode AR a might look
like this where we have nine electrodes
on one side that are measuring the
activity from electrical activity from
the networks and nine on the other side
and you can kind of program any of these
to do anything that you want nine and N
is quite small compared to a lot of um
electrodes but this is just a a start
that what we did in our system um and so
one one potential approach to using
these n networks is something called
Reservoir Computing that's a bit closer
to uh artificial neuronet Network kind
of implementations uh the idea is you
have your inputs like an artificial
neural network you have your inputs you
have your hidden layers in the middle
and then you have your outputs the main
difference is in Reservoir Computing is
the reservoir system or the in the in
between layers are untouched we do not
touch them in traditional AI the idea is
you use something called back
propagation to change your inputs to get
your outputs you change the the the
weights of your each one of these kind
of nodes to try and match your outputs
with a desired output that you have and
you kind of if the desired output is not
similar to your current output you back
propagate you change the weights of the
middle layers and then you try and make
that a bit closer to the output that's
how traditional amn's work in Reservoir
Computing we just let the network kind
of do its thing we don't change the
weights we just let the inherent physics
um do what it wants and then we train an
out on the outputs we train a very
simple model to try and understand the
outputs from the network and so we can
do the same with physical systems like n
Nano networks where we just take out a
traditional Reservoir system and we put
in our Nano networks so what does that
look like well in a task which I did in
um well a bunch of my collaborators did
prior to me and also I did in my PhD we
have this input signal it's called the
nonlinear transformation task we feed in
an a sinusoidal inpo input just a sign a
simple sine wave to the reservoir system
which is our Nano networks we let them
do their thing we don't touch them they
have some Physics that they do based on
all that kind of interesting stuff that
I explained before we get the linear
readouts from that Network and we uh
train some weight Matrix to try and um
using linear regression very very simple
kind of method to try and convert this
input signal into a different output
signal and the only way that that can
happen is if the reservoir system in the
middle has nonlinear Behavior
interesting kind of
um behaviors pretty much um to try and
that that that can transform that input
signal inherently and that we don't need
to train a very complex system to do um
the other task for example is something
called a memory capacity task where you
have a random input signal that you're
feeding into the reservoir um at each
time point and then you you delay your
signal by however many steps and then
you're trying and Rec trying to
reconstruct the time Point end steps
backwards these are just a couple of
examples don't worry if it's a bit too
confusing but um so what did I do
another thing that I did which was
really interesting in my second paper
was trying to combine these kind of
interesting structures of Nano networks
which make them a lot more
biological with with this res our
Computing uh model and so over here we
have a nanowire network all of these use
the same Nano Network model but we just
changed the the structure so this is an
example of a fully connected uh two
layer Nano network not nano Network
sorry artificial neural network uh fully
random Network a nano Network and a
biological Network called the celegans
and we did we performed these two tasks
and we we showed that the Nano networks
at certain values outperform if not
perform as well as other um types of
networks without the need for these and
most interestingly is these bipartite
networks which we use or these Ann type
structures perform the least effectively
uh when using our models so it shows
that there is an importance in this
biological structure as much as there is
in the biological function which I've
been talking about previously so this
this kind of combination of the two is
the most important animportant aspect
and uh lastly last thing I want to talk
about about the Nano networks this is a
very speedrun introduction into it was
my final paper in my PhD which was
actually trying to take brain
inspired um learning tasks and Implement
them in this biological intelligence so
Reservoir Computing was one way to try
and Implement some kind of AI like task
into this but that's not the point of
this
talk and the point of my project was to
try and get a lot more brain inspired
learning a lot more brain inspired
intelligence those kind of aspects and
so that brings us to this type of task
where I try to implement a brain
inspired learning task uh inspired by a
psychological task called the endb back
task where you give a Target pattern to
uh participants then you give them a
bunch of different patterns and then you
ask them after a certain number of steps
do you remember the original pattern
that I presented to you and that's what
we did to this network we presented a
specific pattern for example specific
pattern number a pattern a and then we
gave it a bunch of different patterns
and then we asked it we wanted to see
how many steps back it can remember that
original step that original pattern
that's pretty much and if it if it uh
recognized the pattern successfully we
uh gave it some external feedback so we
either punished it or rewarded it and um
if it that was in the this what we call
the physical reinforcement um category
and if we had no reinforcement then we
didn't punish it at all we didn't give
it any feedback and we just saw what it
would do and so the results so this is
an example of what it looks like a bit
more um clearly so you if our Target
pattern here is pattern a we give a
bunch of patterns then we give pattern a
then we give a couple of other patterns
and then we ask for patent a again so
this would be three steps back where n
equals three so the N back would be
three and this would be kind of what we
feed into the network on the left is
where the inputs are on the right is
sort of what the output that we wanted
to get associated with and each one of
these patterns has a different output
that is associated with it and what we
saw is that the accuracy this is a bit
of a comp a bit of a you know difficult
thing to look at but pretty much the
square the square um dots are what we
saw experimentally the circle dots uh
what we saw in simulation and the
reinforcement so the the what we see
with with the reinforcement so giving
them reward and punishment is at the top
here and what we see without giving them
a reward and punishment is at the bottom
so interestingly enough at this is the
number of steps back where we presented
that original um pattern so for example
at n back equals seven the original
pattern would be right at the start and
there' be a bunch of other patterns and
then we'd ask it again and so what we
see is that without any reinforcement
there is this gradual decay of memory
over time for that patent and that makes
a lot of sense humans are pretty bad at
this task as well we forget quite easily
after about seven steps as well so
that's quite an interesting thing but
what's really interesting is when we
implement this reward and Punishment uh
application which is based in biological
reward and Punishment something called
supervised
learning um and reinforcement learning
these two things combined we see a
massive increase in with in memory for
this uh patternn and this this
um this uh yeah the target um
importantly we also saw that activity
when we had two Targets so if we had
like a target a and then we swapped and
asked for Target B it managed to
remember both of those at the same time
um which is really interesting we
haven't pushed that to the limits but
that's a really interesting aspect and
so that shows that we can get this kind
of biologically inspired learning
mechanisms to give us some interesting
activities in this quite complex
biological inspired
system uh how does that look I've got a
video hopefully that will work on me no
oh yep yep yep we got there come on you
can do it okay maybe I need to select
[Music]
the sorry pointer options turn off laser
pointer play so this is an example of
without the reinforcement we have our
inputs on the right here which is a bit
confusing and then we have our Target
pattern this circle Target pattern so
what you wanted what you'd want to see
is a clear path from anywhere around
here to this target meaning that the N
the network is learning to to prioritize
that pathway over time uh without
reinforcement we're seeing that yes
sometimes that path is being formed most
likely when uh you know that signal is
being implemented but a lot of the time
it's it's not it's not really
prioritizing and for on the other hand
in the reinforcement Paradigm you'll see
pretty quickly we start off with this
sort of random kind of path activity and
then you'll see that over time this path
is remembered by the network and
prioritized you do still get other
Pathways but they're slowly kind of
weakened over time but this path is
almost always staying there and that's
the idea behind this reinforcement
learning and and so the network has
remembered that whenever we're given the
input signal we want to go to that
output TP which is really cool to see I
think this is a really cool video and
there's a summary image of what happens
over time this is flipped so the inputs
in out on the left sorry I know it's
annoying but um the pretty much the red
regions are the regions that are
strengthened between this when we give
reinforcement and we don't give
reinforcement and the blue regions are
what are weakened so the network is
effectively learning to to weaken these
Pathways and strengthen these Pathways
similar to what you might you know you
might say it's similar to this pruning
activity or strengthening activity in a
synaptic kind of uh brain like activity
and and strengthening of synapses which
is really really interesting um really
cool that we managed to see this so
that's quite a lot of a lot of
information how does this even link into
what I'm doing now so that that was my
PhD right now I'm working on real
neurons at cortical labs and you know
neuromorphics are really cool especially
neuromorphic nany networks they try and
replicate the brain they try and
replicate well in a a much smaller scale
neurons and synapses they do it in this
nonlinear type of activation this really
interesting structure and function um
combination that mimics that of neurons
and synapses but they're not neurons and
synapses and so we know that that
neurons and synapses and other types of
cells lead to really cool stuff you know
I'm sitting here and talking to you
because my neurons and My Gal cells and
my interneurons and all that kind of
cool stuff works together to allow me to
speak to think to breathe to do all the
cool things that I can and we're not at
the stage where neuromorphic Nano or
other neuromorphic systems can do that
they can do a lot of really interesting
stuff they can definitely reduce the
amount of energy requirements that we
have but we're definitely not at a stage
where we can Implement that so why not
try do it in neurons we know that
neurons can do it let's try and do that
and that's what cortical Labs is trying
to do so pretty much what we do very
very briefly is we take um uh induced
plur poent stem cells we take a blood
sample from a donor uh a human donor
very very non-invasive simple procedure
we take some blood like you would at a
blood test or you know if you're
donating blood and the amazing
biologists in our team managed to
convert it into something called inter
uh induced pururin stem cells which
means cells that can be reprogrammed to
be any type of cell and we do this uh we
we change these ipscs in indued
polyprotein stem cells into something
called neuronal cultures uh or neural
cells that are very much cells that are
in the cortex very similar to cells that
you and me have in fact if the blood
sample is from you those cells would be
exact would have the exact genome that
you have so we've seen that in patients
who have epilepsy if we take their blood
the cells that we take also have
epilepsy which is really interesting we
can also take it from mice embryos or
other types of animals which a lot of
other people do and then what really is
cool about and differentiates cortical
Labs is we teach them to play games and
we do that using the free energy
principle which you know where I had to
bring in some active inference related
stuff and so that's sort of what we did
in our first paper we presented uh we
modeled this kind of pong environment
the game pong hopefully most of you are
um know this game and the neurons we
tell the neurons we put them on this
chip similar to what I showed in the
nanoes um and we tell them you are the
paddle control the paddle based on this
kind of structure this setup that we
give you and try and predict where the
ball's going to go and the way we do
that is we give them either an
unpredictable feedback or a predictable
feedback um and when they miss the ball
we give them this unpredictable random
kind of feedback and when they hit the
ball they get a predictable sensory
feedback and this fits quite nicely with
the 3 fre energy principle the idea that
we're trying to minimize the randomness
and try and get some predictable
interesting behavior in in order to sort
of maximize our reward and maximize our
understanding of the environment uh we
also give a silent feedback where
nothing happens so the ball just
continues just as a control um and
what's really interesting and I didn't
uh didn't actually include the graph but
I can refer you all to the papers and
I'm sure Brett the CEO of or the CSO of
my company has spoken a couple of times
here um so you may be familiar with that
but we see that when we give this
predictive predictable sensory feedback
the neurons learn to play this game very
very quickly within 5 to 20 minutes of
playing the game and they play it at
statistically significant statistically
better than a pardon me than average or
than chance uh would expect and so this
kind of encoding scheme where we're just
giving this predictable versus
unpredictable sensory feedback that's
the only encoding that we're giving them
we see quite interesting um you know
support for the free energy principle
being used in this kind of neural based
system so there's a lot of stuff that
I've cover today
um there's still so many questions left
I'm more than happy to answer those
questions ask raise more questions um if
anyone wants to ask me in person this is
my email here ad me on LinkedIn I'm love
to chat to anyone and everyone about
this you know 40 minutes it took in the
end um is not enough to cover everything
that I did but I hope it gave a nice
overview and a nice start for people to
um go in and and try and understand and
ask questions so thank you very much to
my supervisor for my PhD my current
bosses and and workmates and for you
guys for having me and for listening and
I yeah look forward to your questions
thank you so much that was absolutely
fascinating that was amazing um yeah I
have so many different question I don't
even know where to start I mean the the
first the main thing I was wondering
about is when you were showing the the
networks with the mback test which was
super interesting Nano networks and you
were talking about reward and Punishment
I was quite interesting how Implement
that but then then you show the um the
work at Cal Labs with pong and it's
about unpredictable so is it a similar
type of reward and punishment that you
did with your simulation with your um
Nan wire networks to that so
unfortunately I hadn't I wasn't aware of
uh active inference for energy principle
all that cool stuff when I was doing my
PhD that was I was introduced to that at
cical Labs I would have loved to try
that on these Nano I imagine it would be
a fantastic way of doing this um we did
something more similar to what you would
imagine in gradient descent but also
this kind of feedback so in a sense
we're trying to give a more uh not maybe
not predictable but we're trying to
match what the output of the network is
with what the expected output is so
maybe that is in a little bit like a
predictable kind of trying to increase
the predictability pretty much what we
did is we changed the can you see my
mouse or do I need the um oh you can't
see my okay great which pretty much what
we did is we changed the voltage of the
um the desired output electrode um and
so if the correct paths were being uh
formed because this is a physical system
and it's a metal system at the end of
the day you get this kind of path of
lease resistance uh forming from where
your sources where your inputs are to
where your drain is the drain is pretty
much just a grounding you know a zero
voltage kind of thing and but you can
play around with that voltage it doesn't
have to be zero you can increase it you
can decrease it you can increase and
decrease the other ones and so we
implemented something similar to
gradient descent on these uh voltages on
these electrodes and when voltage is
increased for example then you imagine
there's
less current or less current will flow
to that um to that electrode and when
voltage is decreased more current will
flow to the electric so on a very basic
level that's sort of what we implemented
but we saw that wasn't enough that
really wasn't enough to train it it
needed this rewarding kind of thing so
we needed to give some kind of threshold
that when that's reached we increase it
it was a bit more complex than that but
that's pretty much the idea behind what
we did thank you okay very interesting
cool
yeah doeses anyone else have any
questions yeah I would have one question
really thank you thank you um so you
started your talk with um motivating it
with the energy consumption of the brain
correct really low so can you give us a
kind of rough estimate of how much these
nanobiosystems
right they're tiny tiny tiny on the on
the scales of Watts you know we're
talking even even significantly lower
than that um the only energy that's kind
of being used in the system is what you
pump in from the you know the the inputs
that you give it so you have to give
some kind of voltage as an input or you
know and then some current is is formed
from that but the system itself the
beauty of this is because of it's a you
know it's a fully connected kind of
physical system we can solve the weights
automatically using kovs laws of current
and and and voltage it's it's just a
physics problem at the end of the day
and so physics just does it for us this
the spreading out of the voltage the
spreading out of the conduct of of all
that stuff as I showed if I go back here
right all this stuff that we see here
the spreading out of this kind of
activation happens inherently based on
the structure of the network and that's
why it's so important to try and
understand that structure and combine it
with a function so when you think about
it that way that's significantly lower
energy requirements than trying to
change each weight individually of each
one of these you know Junctions over and
over and over and over again to better
you know get get a better result okay uh
how many signups are typically could you
realize in such a physical system for
sure in our simulations we use
significantly smaller simulations
because that's what requires a lot of
energy to simulate um we use about 100
to 700 wires in the actual system tens
of thousands if not hundreds of
thousands of of wires per per system the
really other interesting thing is each
one of these systems will be unique so
you'll have a slightly different
structure a slightly different kind of
way that it's uh implemented and a lot
of people think oh that would make it
function significantly differently but
we don't see that we see you know
standard kind of characteristics
obviously there's variance but you you
know the same is with humans and with
brain you see very different structures
and very
different you know experiences that
humans have and there is a variance in
in in our who we are but for much of the
case our activity and our the way we
function is quite similar at the end of
the day okay yeah but um in in the
systems you actually really realized
physically
um how many so I guess if you have like
10 thousands of wires um only a a subset
of those would actually form correct
functional potential synoptic
connections right so there's probably
are to are like electrically isolated
from each other right so I guess that
100% so the really nice thing about
these for now is that they're
two-dimensional and so because they're
two-dimensional a lot more of the wires
cross over each other in kind of
separated regions so you wouldn't you
wouldn't get for example the right
region connected to the left region
right um and so that makes it a lot
simpler to model when you start getting
three-dimensional models you get this
kind of you know wrapping around and a
lot of different connections connecting
to each other so there could be a lot
more connections or a lot less
connections it doesn't necessarily mean
that when a wire crosses over another
wire a perfect connection is formed so
it's quite difficult to expect this and
model it that's why we have to rely on
uh electrical characterization and
seeing these kind of conductance Curves
here right comparing the conduct curves
verus with the models that we have with
the actual uh the actual physical
systems that's how we do that kind of
model okay yeah thank you and for the
for the dish brain for the like
biological cells so I mean the the brain
is actually fairly structured right in
the end yes correct so are you working
in the direction of also using a bit
more of the brains morphology Absolut
cell types and also
layers so we have a whole bunch of
different cell types that we have we do
all sorts of combinations of excitatory
inhibitory cells gal cells asites all
that kind of stuff um whereas currently
still also working on two-dimensional
layouts or two and a half dimensional
layouts but there's we've had some
collaborations with people for example
John Hopkins University in America um
which I believe I can talk about um
hopefully I can talk about uh where we
work with organoids um which are
three-dimensional tiny little kind of
cell structures they're not fully you
know structured like what you'd see in
any kind of brain organ um structure but
they're a lot more similar to a tiny
kind of brain structure and so what
would really I mean my end goal in this
is to try and stack chips together you
know so a chip might be have a
two-dimensional structure but then you
can have it um touching another chip
forming you know forming long
connections across that kind of barrier
with with another chip and then your
first chip might act as some kind of
sensory region and your second chip
might be a processing region right and
then you can form these Pudo structures
in that way um what's beautiful about
neurons compared to nanoes which I think
is another reason and I didn't touch
upon this is neurons self organized
after they're um placed down so with
Nano eyes you put them down they self
organize and they never move again you
know they will never move again because
they're silver wires and you cannot move
neurons automatically are constantly
looking for connections constantly
changing their structure based on the
input that is given to them so you know
they will form inherently structures as
well um and we're really we're exploring
that we're exploring how that happens
when you're giving them predictable
feedback how that happens when you're
giving them unpredictable feedback how
it happens when you give them no
feedback at all and these are all the
kind of questions that we're trying to
you know um answer at cortical Labs
which is I think I find extremely
interesting okay thank you it's
interesting um I'm really interested in
the applications which you also briefly
touched on um in terms of when you said
you get a donor with epilepsy and then
you um their celles also exhibit
epilepsy which then leads me on to
thinking about well the applications of
this could you potentially see this as
sort of like a neural aesthetic or
something where um say with someone with
epilepsy they have that little part of
their brain with their High
concentration of epileptic cells removed
sometimes I think that already happens
now with EP epilepsy surgery could you
see this almost of of them being an
implant where you've taken their cells
you've edited out the epileptic Gene if
you if it was able to be identified then
you reprogram them into neurons
basically without epilepsy and then sort
of put them back into the bit that you
could take out I think that would be
absolutely fascinating um I think
there's so many different ways this can
go down
luckily I'm not the one who has to
decide that I have a lot of ideas myself
uh but uh I think one really key thing
that we I should highlight is you know
what what you mentioned is really really
interesting and some people might think
oh that's currently already being done
in brain computer interfaces right
there's a key difference between what
we're doing and what brain computer
interfacing is pretty much the idea with
brain computer interfacing is you have a
chip that reads the activity of the
brain right and it spits out whatever
that activity is and then you have some
very clever algorithms to understand
what that original signal was in the
brain so for example you might think of
a tennis game and then you get some kind
of uh electrical signal that represents
a tennis game and eventually these uh
algorithms will pick up that you're
thinking of a tennis game now that's
really cool really important going to
help a lot of people but there's a s
significant limitation in that
whereas we cannot we we don't know what
the brain is doing still to create those
images right of a tennis game why are
certain regions lighting up to represent
that and and brain computer interfacing
is not giving us any information about
that you know it's just trying to
reconstruct what is already being taking
place and what we're trying to do is
we're actually trying to figure out the
algorithms and the encoding schemes you
know whether it's free energy principle
whatever else might might be hopefully
it is something as as straightforward as
the free energy principle um where we
want to actually write those encoding
processes into these neurons teach them
the output that we want them to give us
rather than just interpret what the
output is so we're doing the encoding
into the networks and the decoding
whereas the brain computer interface is
sort of just the decoding and so you
know in an epilepsy kind of um situation
you might be able to have a chip like
that in in the brain this is just you
know pure conjecture but it could be
interesting um and you feed in some kind
of input into that chip which
programs the cells that it's you know
that are being controlled by that to
give a different output than the
epileptic output that we're already
seeing right and so rather than just
saying oh that's an epileptic fit we can
predict that it's like okay yeah we can
predict it but now we can actually do
something to change it right we can
actually change it with some kind of
input I like to imagine in a very
futuristic kind of application of this
hopefully not too futuristic but in a
very
futuristic application of this you know
in The Matrix when Neo is plugged in and
he suddenly goes you know he his eyes go
blank and they're uploading all this
stuff to him and he wakes up and he goes
I know Kung Fu that's sort of the the
kind of very futuristic U sci-fi
application of of what we're actually
doing we're actually encoding Kung Fu
into these
cells and then trying to replicate that
yeah that is absolutely fascinating yeah
I was actually going to ask you sort of
what are you most excited about in this
field like what do you see coming ABS
future for you would it be sort of the
brain computer interface space I think
the brain computer interface space is
fascinating you know we're seeing really
interesting
companies even local Australian
companies like synchron overtaking these
multi-billion dollar uh organizations in
in this uh space um we're going to see a
lot more interesting kind of uh
predictions of what people who might not
be able to communicate normally um and
and reconstructing their thoughts and
and what they're actually trying to you
know represent um and so that's going to
transform a lot of people's lives it's
going to trans form medicine in that
sense but what I'm much more interested
in you know it's still very interesting
and it's going to be really cool in the
near future but what I'm much more
interesting in in is this idea of can we
write things into neurons can we program
neurons to give us the kind of outputs
that we want rather than just you know
interpreting what they're already doing
and that's what we're doing a cical labs
in the long run um you know it might
take a long time to get there but really
really interested to do that very cool
and then something which obviously
people are talking about a lot is like
the ethics of AI and the explainability
and the transparency of AI which is a
current problem with the you know
blackbox methods that we have one of the
things I found interesting about active
inference is people talk about how you
can actually have much more transparent
and explainable AI potentially and I see
what you're doing with the do you think
with the Nano wi networks you also have
the opportunity for that because you can
actually go in and don't know we didn't
get on to how you actually visualize and
analyze them which is interesting but
like do you think that this type of AI
would be more explainable than sort of
traditional artificial neural networks
oh without a question I mean you know
the reservoir Computing approach that I
that I touched on does use that black
box approach which is why I didn't
really like it I used it for the first
couple of um papers that I worked on and
then was sort of like this is not how
the brain works maybe it is maybe there
are some aspects of it but the brain is
not a black box I mean to us it is but
you know there are so many little pieces
that work together to you know create
these kind of uh emerging properties and
there's rules that govern that and
there's structures that govern that and
so there must be a way to implement
those kind of rules into some into these
systems and then be able to actually see
them learning and that's you know that
video that I showed you can see how it's
changing over time which is very very
different to these blackbox approaches
where we don't even know why weight you
know why different weight weight
changing results in this kind of
learning um I think in neurons you can
do all sorts of cool calcium Imaging you
can do infrared kind of microscopy I I'm
not a biologist so I'm sorry to my team
if I was wrong about that but you know
we have them on these transparent cells
arrays so we can actually see we can
take images you know we can put them in
the incubator play a bunch of long games
take them out take some images see how
they've shifted see what's happened and
try and correlate that with the activity
that's a much more transparent way of
learning in my opinion very cool so it's
almost like we have more energy
efficiency we have more explainability
and we have like these opportunities for
personalization almost like with your
own uh cells in the in the chip which I
think it's really cool it's a it's a
very exciting Direction I think for for
lots of different Technologies I guess
not just brain computer interfaces as
well for sure and you know I think
what's really interesting is how we can
combine these Technologies like
neuromorphics with neurons neuromorphics
are trying to replicate neurons is there
a way we can use neuromorphics to kind
of act as like you know eyes you know
our eyes do this pre-processing kind of
activity where you take in an a light
signal an electrical signal convert it
through some kind of cell you know
activity into a more understandable
signal for your occipital L and your
other regions of your brain can we use
neuromorphic systems like Nano networks
to take in a raw input and output a more
biological like signal which then
neurons would be a lot more receptive to
you know I said we'd really like to
encode these write things into neurons
and get them to do things that way but
the question of how to do that is a
really difficult question um otherwise
people would have figured it out by now
um we have a lot of theories but one of
those might be as simple as let's use
these technologies that are taking in
simple in or complex inputs and making
them into a more biological like output
based on just their inherent properties
and then feed that you know interface
with a biological system who knows maybe
that'll be a really cool way of of
getting that kind of encoding and
writing in method so that's something
that I'm really interested in in
marrying those two worlds together as
well okay I'm conscious I don't want to
go too much over time but I do have a
little bit more got a little bit more my
I've actually got as much time as you
need so that's very cool um anyone else
please jump in with questions but did
just want to touch on um something which
I'd heard about with your work before
where you mentioned about the quantum um
aspects of the silver Nano wire Network
yes not a quantum computer scientists by
any means but I'm interested in this
because there's sort of this debate in
Neuroscience about whether or not
there's a Quantum brain like the brain
Quantum um maybe you know for our
faction um there's been some suggestions
some theories about that's how we we
smell with with Quantum tunneling and
the AL faction receptors but the rest of
the brain people seem to be the jury
seems to be still out and I'm just
interested in your network seemed to use
you you mentioned that there was like
some Quantum tunneling forming the
bridges potenti is that is that your
work or was it just you know something
which um is interesting but wasn't
really you examined so it was actually
more of my colleagues Joel and we have a
paper in nature com's uh nature
Communications about that so I can I can
definitely share that with people if you
Google my name it's the first thing that
will come up um but yeah I love that
we're covering all the buzz words here
it's
fantastic so yes the quantum tunneling
or we call it electrod tunneling um we
see this Behavior it's sort of the only
way we can explain this um and so that's
sort of why we've hypothesized and
Joel's shown some evidence for this but
the idea is that you start with a no
Bridge here on the left for example and
over time you get this fully connected
bridge but that doesn't it's not like an
immediate kind of response that takes
time to sort of the ions flow slowly
through that it's quite quick but it
it's not an immediate response but what
we start to see is if for example the
bridge is kind of semiformed and let's
imagine these two dots here aren't there
these two little um balls at the end or
ions aren't there you can see you start
seeing these weird fluctuations of
conductance before that switch is fully
formed and that's explained by this
Quantum tun or Electro tunneling of
electrod jumping through the gap between
the whatever leftover Gap is is there
just by chance um and and and that
actually accounts for really interesting
uh behaviors that I haven't covered
today I don't really fully understand
them myself that's not my area of
expertise but Joel has explored them and
has some really interesting theories
about how that might affect the networks
one example is this idea of criticality
so criticality is sort of uh the theory
that you know biological systems or a
lot of systems actually real world
systems um have maximal information
processing at the edge of criticality or
the edge of chaos so uh chaotic system
is one that is sort of completely
unpredictable has full chaotic activity
and and ordered on the other hand an
ordered system is something that nothing
interesting can happen because you can
you know exactly what's going to happen
it's ful predictable you know every
single aspect of it but somewhere in the
the middle somewhere in between where
you're not too chaotic there's still
quite a lot of unpredictable Behavior
but there is a predictability to that
chaoticness it's called the edge of
chaos that's where things seem to thrive
life seems to thrive and we've seen
criticality in Nano networks we've seen
criticality in our neurons as well in
cortical labs and one of these ideas is
that potentially
uh the electrod tunneling might um might
help tune the system into this critical
State wow okay we don't really fully
understand it if you're really
interested in that the paper is a really
cool um uh summary of that I guess I'll
get the link off you and I'll make sure
you put it into sounds great YouTube
description um yeah because I'm really
interested in sort of what these
synthetics systems can then tell us in
turn about the brain for those sort of
things we've been uncertain about for a
long time like whether or not the brain
users Quantum and it's interesting
actually as well because there was a Loi
chip and they used that the neuromorphic
nose um and that performed quite well so
it would be interesting if you could
sort of combine with these type of
networks that maybe do have the quantum
effects and sort of test out these more
quantum theories of our faction that
would be pretty cool for sure I I I
think there's so much you know to
explore here um look I I have maybe been
unreasonable to some of the neuromorphic
chips like ly he in this talk I know I
only briefly spoke about it there's
definitely space for that they're doing
amazing things um there's some really
cool learning algorithms and some really
awesome people working on this stuff uh
I think my perspective from this is that
we want to try and replicate more brain
likee learning and more brain-like
activity and for that we need a
structure that is more brain-like as
well um the structure function behavior
and and and relationship is key in my
opinion to unlock in the emergence the
emerg properties in you know the brain
um and so a lot of those chips lack that
um and hopefully people you know will
work more and more on these brain
inspired systems um and and start to
consider the structural element of it as
well because it is extremely important
and I guess you've spoken about the
nanowire networks and you've also spoken
about the more neuronal networks like
where's your work going the direction
like are you moving away from the Nano y
networks or can you see like a hybrid of
of both actually being quite useful in
the future yeah so I think I touched on
that briefly you know marrying the two
nanoes and and um and neurons together
as sort of this like encoding Bridge or
something like that that's you know
unofficially something that I'm
interested in um I'd love to explore
that whether or not that's something
that I'll have the time and the
resources to do
we'll see um but that's you know
definitely where my interests lie um I'm
very happy to be able to apply you know
my knowledge and my expertise in these
kind of algorithm development and brain
learning in actual neurons so that's
sort of what my focus is on at the
moment but I'm still very much in touch
with my supervisor and my team at
University of Sydney and you know we've
got a paper coming out um later this
year or I guess next year um
or did it just come out now I think it
just recently came out actually what am
I talking about gosh what what year is
it it just recently came out in in in
nature as well um so nature comes so
yeah go check that one out as well very
cool okay has anybody else got any
questions before we wrap
up cool okay I've got one last question
one thing I'm always curious about is um
if there's any sort of major problems in
your field that you want someone to go
out and solve almost like CU anyone
watch and they might be listen they
might be working on some obscure little
problem and um do you have any asks of
it could be you know this mathematical
theorem or you know create some Hardware
that we can do this weird thing with
like what would be your main asks I
think for anybody listening who might
work on something weird and wonderful so
I think for that let me just go back to
the final slide again I know I'm jumping
around back and forth but I think what
I'm working on most at the moment and
what I think is the most important thing
for our work and
for anyone who's working in this space
is figuring out that encoding Paradigm
what is it that the eyes do that the
ears do that the nose does actually I
think the nose does it least but that
our sensory organs do so well to
encode you know what might be seen as
nonsense information you know uh there's
obviously structures to it and and it's
not nonsense but it it it's
you know light or sound or very
different forms of information into
something that the brain can understand
and make inferences about you know and
not just make inferences build models of
the world to try and replicate it you
know active inference is all about
trying to understand that um how do we
do that obviously that is a huge
question but in a simpler way how do we
encode a simple electrical impulse or a
string a temporal
sequence into something that neurons can
understand okay and we can we can
actually elicit different outputs from
it very cool okay so if anybody's
listening and they're working on please
get in touch Alon because uh please do
yeah that would definitely catalyze the
field I guess solving those kinds of
questions and problems if we can solve
that then yeah I mean we'll be having
very different conversations in the next
few years I think very very exciting
conversation yeah well hopefully the
more stream will still be going we can
bring you back I would love that I would
absolutely love that okay right I guess
we'll end there have you got any last
comments or anything before we end the
recording just feel free to email me
reach out I think science needs to
really be open and collaborative and you
know I do work for a company but I'm
also still very much about open source
work and you know I
will you and
add me on LinkedIn and let's just keep
chatting let's just keep answering these
questions right thank you so much and
thank you everybody for listening and
for joining the call today and thank you
for having me I'll see you later